Guide to the Christopher Phillips Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
- June 1973 - August 1975, Los Angeles (With an Interlude in Alabama): Gay Community Services Center and Highland Park Collective, Series VI
  - Asian-American: Japanese-American relocation. Interview with Ruth Yamazaki, editor of the Kashu Mainichi newspaper in Los Angeles and a controversial figure because of her statements that camp "wasn't all that bad" and her publicly voiced questions about the loyalty of at least the Japan-born issei generation at the time of the war; she was evacuated from Manzanar for her own safety after the riot. My handwritten notes of interview [I will decipher if there is interest]; transcribed interview, cut up for editing; the edited version, as submitted for publication in Amerasia Journal [it was not published]. Interview took place on February 12, 1975, at Kashu Mainichi, in Little Tokyo, Los Angeles, 1975 January-August (Box 31, Folder 73)
  - Asian-American: Japanese-American relocation. Interview with Edison Uno [1929-76], teacher and activist and son-in-law of Saburo Kido, president of the Japanese American Citizens League 1940-46, about his father-in-law's and JACL's policies in response to the relocation order. My written notes [I will decipher if there is interest]; transcribed interview; the interview as submitted to Amerasia Journal [it was not published]. Interview took place at his home in San Francisco, February 17, 1975. Other photocopied writings by Edison Uno that he gave me, 1975 January-August (Box 31, Folder 74)
  - Asian-American, Japanese-American relocation. Interview with Bill Nakasaki, key figure in the Terminal Island Japanese-American fishing community in San Pedro Bay, California, before the war. Typed list of questions; my handwritten notes of interview [I will decipher if there is interest.] Interview took place February 14, 1975 in Montebello, California [it was not published], 1975 January-August (Box 31, Folder 75)
  - Asian-American, Japanese-American relocation, Manzanar internment camp, California. Material from Sue Kunitomi Embrey and the Manzanar Committee; photocopy of May 26, 1942, Japanese American Citizens League report on conditions at Manzanar; fliers for the 1975 annual Manzanar pilgrimage; 1974 state feasibility study recommending Manzanar be made a state park; correspondence with Embrey about publishing the interviews in Amerasia Journal; note from me about my 2004 gift to the Manzanar National Historic Site of two pieces of Japanese calligraphy by Joyce Black, 1975 January-August (Box 31, Folder 76)
- August 1975 - October 1976, Taiwan (Plus Travels): In Asia at Last, and Starting a Career, Series VII
  -- From August 15, 1975, to August 17, 1976, I lived in Taipei, Taiwan, where I studied Chinese, taught English, had a great group of close friends, got my first job in magazines, acted as an occasional extra in Shaw Brothers movies, sang with a blue-grass band a couple of times, did fun drugs, explored gay life, had an important relationship with a man there, and generally enjoyed wild bohemian Christopher Isherwood-type student days. Our large communal apartment on Tung An Street in Taipei became sort of like a collective, and was the scene of a lot of great parties.
  -- August 29, 1975, my brother David F. Phillips arrived in Taiwan to take a teaching job in the town of Taichung. He stayed until the spring and was a frequent visitor to Tung An Street.
  -- September 21, 1975, I met Vincent (born Taiwan, 1955), with whom I had a very important relationship, which lasted until spring.
  -- In November 1975, my mother visited me in Taiwan and with her I made my first visit to Hong Kong and, after she left, Macao. This was more the Asia I was hoping to find (with an old-fashioned British touches as a bonus), and I decided I wanted to return there some day to work as a journalist. (See Series IX.)
  -- Early April 1976, I got my first magazine job, as Managing Editor in charge of Taiwan Trade Monthly, with a brief to remake the magazine from scratch. I had never been in a magazine office before, but I immediately knew this was what I had always wanted at do. I realized that this was my route to joining the big world. It had glamour and an outlet for my imagination and love of making big plans. I enlisted my friends as reporters, and it was the start of my publishing career.
  -- Spring 1976, I was accepted by Louisiana State University into its Master of Social Work program; my aim was to become qualified as a therapist, essentially in a continuation of my work at the Gay Community Services Center. I was also offered a scholarship and a teaching assistantship at LSU, which would have been the cushion I needed to make my re-entry into the United States, where I had no money and no place to live. But I must have had a sense that this goal had become outdated, because the desire to travel was stronger than the desire to head to Baton Rouge in August to start classes.
  -- On August 17, 1976, I left Taiwan to go traveling, part of the time with one or two of my Taipei housemates, part of the time alone. This trip took me to Hong Kong, Thailand, Bali (Kuta Beach, before the first large hotel was built), Singapore, Malaysia (where we hitchhiked and I experienced a Chinese opium den in a small village), Korea and Japan (where I stayed with Joyce Block).
  -- While traveling, I heard from my brother David F. Phillips, who was by this time living in San Francisco, that I could collect unemployment insurance from my pre-Taiwan work if I filed my claim by October 31. This was the re-entry money I needed: I cut my trip short and headed back to Los Angeles.
  -- On October 22, 1976, I returned to Los Angeles.
  -- Students in the 1970's during their Wanderjahr. As it did for Christopher Isherwood, this included odd jobs teaching English, in my case with families, at small institutes, a high school, and the diplomatic training college of the moribund Nationalist Chinese Ministry of Foreign Affairs (which had, nonetheless, a great cafeteria).
  -- Life in Taiwan, 1975-76, just after the death of Chiang Kai-shek, when it was still more or less under military rule.
  -- Finally getting to Asia, with a certain amount of disappointment because gray-concrete, motorcycle-filled Taipei was not the traditional China of my dreams.
  -- Gay life in Taiwan and elsewhere.
  -- The 1976 Gay Pride Parade in San Francisco as described by my brother David F. Phillips, who saw it from his Polk Street window.
  -- The Southeast Asia backpackers route in the 1970's -- when the first Lonely Planet guide, Southeast Asia on a Shoestring, was still circulating quasi-underground and before Kuta Beach, Bali, had even one big hotel.
  -- Gay Community Services Center and Highland Park Collective: many letters from this period discuss ongoing developments in both places, and I have marked them accordingly.
  -- Social work graduate programs in the United States, Canada and Hong Kong, with which I was in touch by mail.
  -- My ongoing relationship with Ed Sanders, much of which was worked out in our correspondence; this correspondence also has a lot of material about the Gay Community Services Center and the Highland Park Collective.
  -- Starting my career in publishing as managing editor of a magazine-- another example of my running before I could walk.Â But in this case, being a magazine editor was a natural talent and an outlet for my love of creating big plans and schemes, so I did it pretty well.
  1) Names: Many letters from Los Angeles address me by my gay liberation "nom de guerre," Morning Glory, or M.G. for short. Documents in Chinese use my Chinese name, FEI Hai-ch'ing.
  2) Dates often follow the Taiwan system of counting years from the establishment of the Republic of China, with 1911 being Year 1. So 1975 was Year 64 and 1976 was Year 65. The Chinese put the month before the day. Therefore, 65.4.3 means April 3, 1976.
  - Gallery of photographs (photocopies) from the period: my friends, my brother David F. Phillips and I, including views of the apartment at Tung An Street, Taipei, 1975-1976 (Box 32, Folder 1)
  - Pages from my passport that cover this period: I needed a fold-out extra leaf pasted in the passport for all the visa stamps, something I got a kick out of (photocopies: the original is in Series V), 1975-1976 (Box 32, Folder 2)
  - Journey to Taiwan, including last few days in San Francisco en route: arrangements for staying initially at International House, Taipei; "plane letter" from my mother, to be opened on the journey, 1975 August (Box 32, Folder 3)
  - Address book, bought in August 1975 and used in Taiwan (Box 32, Folder 4)
  - Appointment book, with photograph (photocopies) of my boyfriend, Vincent, pasted in the back [original book: pages from the pre-Taiwan period were photocopied for Series V.], 1975 August-December (Box 32, Folder 5)
  - Letters overseas to and from me. [those that contain references to the Gay Community Services Center or Highland Park Collective are marked GCSC or HPC], 1975 August-December (Box 32, Folder 6)
  - Letters from me to my mother, 1975 August-1976 August (Box 32, Folder 7)
  - Letters from me to Ed Sanders: some include references to Gay Community Services Center and Highland Park Collective, 1975 August-1976 August (Box 32, Folder 8-9)
  - Letters from Ed Sanders to me: they contain a lot of discussion of the Gay Community Services Center and Highland Park Collective, 1975 August-1976 August (Box 32, Folder 10)
  - My life, Taipei: relics, including a rough floor plan, showing who had what room, of our apartment on Tung An Street, Taipei [Tung An Jye, Lane 92, Alley 8, No. 2, Taipei, Tel: 391-8083]; correspondence with others in Asia, including my brother David F. Phillips, first during his stay in Okinawa and then at his teaching job in Taichung, central Taiwan; English teaching materials I devised for my students; ephemera and relics from the November first visit to Hong Kong with my mother, 1975 August-December (Box 32, Folder 11-12)
  - My favorite photograph (photocopy) of Vincent, 1975 (Box 32, Folder 13)
  - Taiwan friends: a list of key names, prepared for this archive [I have clues, not always listed here, concerning the whereabouts of some of them]. Also photographs (photocopies): Pat Shade, who now lives in Hawaii [one from 1975 passport, one with Cathy Obern, one with her Chinese friend "CooCoo"]; Sufi Richardson; Lynda Reed, plus one of her husband, Bruce Fier, and son, Zach, at about age 2; a 1980 newspaper mention of Russell Long in Los Angeles, 1975-2005 (Box 32, Folder 14)
  - Fiction ideas, from 1985, based on my experiences in Taiwan during this period: some of these images are real, some imagined, 1975-1976 (Box 32, Folder 15)
  - My Chinese language studies, Taiwan: includes my notebooks, 1975-1976 (Box 33, Folder 16-17)
  - Applications to social work schools [Louisiana State University and others], and M.A. program at East-West Center, University of Hawaii; includes personal essays, 1975-1976 (Box 33, Folder 18)
  - University of Hong Kong social work program: correspondence and application [this is one of the last gasps of my Chinatown interest], 1975-1976 (Box 33, Folder 19)
  - Appointment book [Taiwan, then Los Angeles], 1976 January-December (Box 33, Folder 20)
  - Letters overseas to and from me, including correspondence with my brother David F. Phillips after his return to U.S.A. [those that contain references to the Gay Community Services Center and Highland Park Collective are marked GCSC and HPC], 1976 January-August (Box 33, Folder 21)
  - My life, Taipei: includes relics and local and Asian letters, 1976 January-August (Box 33, Folder 22-23)
  - Gay, Taipei: New Park [Hsin Gung Yüan], the gay cruising spot in Taipei after dark. Aerial photograph of the park, taken in almost exactly my era, I estimate; also a short explanatory note by me, 1976 (Box 33, Folder 24)
  - Taiwan Trade Monthly: two of the issues I edited; my business card, in English and Chinese, as Managing Editor; piece of stationery; funny note that my housemate Mary Ellenbecker [now Johnson] wrote to me when she was working as Senior Editor of the magazine; an exact reconstruction, written by me later in Los Angeles, of the strange sequence of events that got me this job, which turned out to be the start of my career in publishing, 1976 April-August (Box 33, Folder 25)
  - The New York Times, Taiwan advertising supplement for Bicentennial: I wrote the ad copy, 1976 July 4 (Box 33, Folder 26)
  - Gay, United States military: Gay Awareness Workshop proposal for U.S. military Family Assistance Center, Tienmu, Taipei, 1976 April (Box 34, Folder 27)
  - Gay, San Francisco: my brother David F. Phillips's description of watching the Gay Pride Parade from his window on Polk and Pine Streets; one page, typewritten, 1976 June (Box 34, Folder 28)
  - Taiwan ephemera: elegant Chinese stationery; pre- and post-1949 Republic of China currency and stamps; Kuomintang memorabilia [much of this was collected on later visits, especially 1978 and 1995, but these things were very much on my mind during the period I lived there], 1976- (Box 34, Folder 29)
  - Address book, typed on sheets of paper, for traveling: who and what was current, 1976 July (Box 34, Folder 30)
  - Travels in Southeast Asia, Korea and Japan, partly with Pat Shade and/or Mary Ellenbecker [now Johnson], partly alone [Hong Kong, August 17-29, with overnight in Macau on August 18; Bangkok, August 29-September 1; Kuta Beach, Bali, September 1-13; Singapore, September 13-20; Malaysia, September 20-October 6, then by train to Thailand; Bangkok, October 7-13; Seoul, October 13-16; Tokyo, October 16-22, staying with Joyce Block in Yokohama; return to Los Angeles, October 22]: material relating to the trip, including letters, relics and ephemera picked up along the way, 1976 August-October (Box 34, Folder 31-33)
- October 1976 - June 1981, Los Angeles Again: Hitting My Stride -Architectural Digest, Jim Ito and My First Book, Series VIII
  Scope and Contents note
  -- October 22, 1976, I arrived back in Los Angeles with no job, almost no money, but the promise of unemployment insurance if I filed my claim by October 31. After a few days at the much-changed Highland Park Collective, I moved in with my friend Stephen Breimer, who had an apartment in Beverly Hills.
  -- Fall 1976, I lived in Beverly Hills, enjoying life without any pressure (and also, in retrospect, enjoying the slow, almost contemplative pace of being in Los Angeles without a car).
  -- Christmas 1976, my mother visited me in Los Angeles. She, Stephen Breimer and a family friend JoAnne Stang (the mother of David Stang, a close Camp Monomoy friend) persuaded me that I was qualified to set my sites high in the professional world.
  -- January 27, 1977, I moved into a small "guest house" garden apartment in the Hollywood Hills and looked for jobs, first in show business public relations, and then in magazines. I got a list of every magazine published in Los Angeles and began calling them one by one, armed with my Managing Editor's title from Taiwan Trade Monthly. One of the magazines on the list was Architectural Digest, which I had never heard of. However, they were on the list, so I called them and was miraculously put straight through to the famous Editor-in-Chief, Paige Rense.
  -- April 11, 1977, I started working at Architectural Digest. I was in heaven at that elegant, world-class place. The white heat of my professional ambition and all my worldwide schemes finally had an arena. I worked there from April 1977 until May 1981. At first I was a freelancer writing captions for the company's first book project, then shifted to the magazine, where I began the Architecture Feature, and was also at various times the editor in charge of the Historic Homes, Gardens and Historic Architecture features; eventually, I added some editorial administrative responsibilities. I also did some feature writing for the magazine.
  -- At some point in 1977 (or 1978), Stephen Breimer and I traded apartments for several months: he moved to my little guest house in the Hollywood Hills and I moved back to Beverly Hills.
  -- On July 23, 1977, I met Jim Ito (born Los Angeles, 1948). It was love at first sight. We lived together until my move to Hong Kong in June 1981.
  -- August 1977, Paige Rense, the Editor-in-Chief of Architectural Digest, asked me to start a new residential Architectural Feature for the magazine. Since I knew nothing about the subject, the architect Frank Israel (1945-96) advised me initially. Eventually, my close friend from Yale, Paul Goldberger, who was then the architecture critic of The New York Times, wrote some of the articles.
  -- February 1978, I was given the title Associate Editor.
  -- May 1978, I visited Taiwan and Hong Kong.
  -- December 1978, I began work on my first book, The Dream Come True: Great Houses of Los Angeles, produced by John Calmann, a British book "packager" (and protégé of Benjamin Sonnenberg), who was an important figure in my life until his death, in 1980. Text was by Brendan Gill (who had also been extremely close to Ben Sonnenberg and who had been an important figure in my life since I read his memoir Here at The New Yorker on the road in Southeast Asia in 1976), and he became a good friend until his death, in 1997). Photographs were by the British photographer Derry Moore (then Viscount Moore, now Earl of Drogheda). I chose the houses, got us access to them, and organized the project in Los Angeles, all of which exposed me to celebrities, local experts, and the city's "high society." I also started giving parties, with the help of a gay couple Roman A. Clef and Michael Leopold, an artist and art critic respectively, who were Los Angeles social gadflies. The bulk of the work on the book took place in 1979 and 1980.
  -- April 1979, I was given the title Associate Managing Editor, which included a lot of the administrative part of the Managing Editor's job.
  -- November and December 1979, I took a trip to Singapore, Malaysia, Japan, Taiwan and Hong Kong.
  -- July 19, 1980, my mother died.
  -- By fall 1980, I was restless at Architectural Digest and presented a proposal to The Los Angeles Times to start a Sunday color magazine there.
  -- Fall 1980, I began contacting magazines in London looking for a job.
  -- January 1981, I made a three-day visit to London for an interview at The Telegraph Sunday Magazine on Fleet Street. It was a secret trip over a long weekend, which added to the fun. I desperately wanted a job there.
  -- March 1981, I set off on a trip to Hong Kong and Tokyo to look for magazine or newspaper jobs. I was offered a job at Asiaweek, a weekly news magazine in Hong Kong, almost immediately, so never went to Tokyo; instead, I darted directly to New York for the second week of the trip to attend to my mother's estate.
  -- Spring 1981, I was trying to get The Telegraph in London to make me an offer: I had a bird in the hand in Hong Kong, but I preferred Fleet Street. No offer came in time.
  -- May 20, 1981, was my last day at Architectural Digest.
  -- June 16, 1981, I left Los Angeles for Hong Kong. I remained overseas for 10 years, until February 13, 1991, the end of the first installment of this archive.
  -- Life in Los Angeles as the disco era of the 70's gave way to the glossy Reagan boom of the 1980's.
  -- Architectural Digestmagazine and my work there.
  -- The beginnings of word processing and fax technology in the magazine industry.
  -- The book The Dream Come True: Great Houses of Los Angeles.
  -- Los Angeles so-called "high society" of the late 1970's and early 1980's.
  -- An autobiographical dossier prepared by Diane Abramson, a Los Angeles celebrity hostess (and possessor of 12 ovens), one of the residents in The Dream Come True.
  -- The gay artist Roman A. Clef and his partner, the critic and social gadfly Michael Leopold (both born 1929). (Gay researchers, note! Theirs is a great story.)
  -- Gay Community Services Center and Highland Park Collective: activities of Jerome Gold (formerly Crickett Bon Bon) in forming an art gallery with Michael Leopold.
  -- Truly making a happy life with someone for the first time. Jim Ito and I lived in (and bought) the house in Hollywood where the "My sister/My mother" scene in the movie Chinatown was filmed.
  -- Several cassettes of readings and classes with psychics in Los Angeles and New York. Also, a numerology reading by Matthew Oliver Goodwin and an astrological reading.
  -- Gay life in Los Angeles, London and New York: three thin files.
  -- Gay visionary architect Roger C. Ferri: one file.
  -- Magazines and newspapers in London, Hong Kong, Tokyo and elsewhere with whom I was in touch.
  -- Correspondence and negotiations with the famous Fleet Street editor John Anstey of The Telegraph Sunday Magazine.
  -- Asian-American: material relating to Jim Ito and the extended Ito and Kuromi families, prominent Japanese-American families in Los Angeles. Jim is a second-generation American ( sansei in Japanese).
  -- My mother's death, and my adjustment to being without parents.
  -- The opening up of the range of possibilities when I realized I was inheriting enough money to provide a small financial cushion (which, in those days of 15% interest rates, seemed like more than it was).
  -- During this period, I read Golda Meir's autobiography, My Life, and that book gave me a sense of Jewish identity for the first time ever. Beginning in 1979, I became very active in Sinai Temple, a Conservative synagogue in Los Angeles. It was my first serious plunge into Judaism as a spiritual path; Conservative Judaism seemed much more authentic to me than the Reform movement of my childhood. Little by little I edged our kitchen in the kosher direction and I developed a secret hope/plan to enter Conservative rabbinical school after a waiting period of about five years in order to let the plan mature.
  -- In my two job searches, I learned again the great lesson my parents had taught me by writing, against all odds, to Eton back in 1966. After wasting time trying to get a foothold in show business public relations through friends of friends, etc., I got my job at Architectural Digest with the simple direct approach, by just picking up the phone and calling systematically. It was this sense of "Anything's possible" that took me on those secret job-hunting trips to London and Hong Kong and got me my next job, overseas. The same approach had worked when I just showed up at Virgin Records in London in 1972 after wasting time with useless letters of introduction in Paris.
  -- Finally having a creative outlet for my creative energy and worldwide scheme-making in a glamorous, first-class place, Architectural Digest. My appetite for work was insatiable, as was my ambition. I found my stride, and hit it.
  1) Originals of photocopied photographs from the Jim Ito Collection are in the possession of James A. Ito, 1991 North Alexandria Avenue, Los Angeles 90027; (323) 664-4316. Each album page or photograph reproduced here has a number that corresponds to a page in his albums.
  2) Some financial records for 1981, especially those from job-hunting trips to London and Asia, are found in the Hong Kong 1981 Series.